<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://cwrc.ca/templates/css/ceww.css"?>
<?xml-model href="http://cwrc.ca/schemas/cwrc_entry.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<CWRC>
    <CWRCHEADER>
        <FILEDESC>
            <TITLESTMT>
                <DOCTITLE>NERVE CWRC Entry Test File - short with pre-existing entity tags</DOCTITLE>
                <DOCAUTHOR>Adapted from file by Canada's Early Women Writers</DOCAUTHOR>
                <DOCAUTHOR>Adapted from Karyn Huenemann and Linnea McNally by Susan Brown</DOCAUTHOR>
            </TITLESTMT>
            <PUBLICATIONSTMT>
                <AUTHORITY>Canada's Early Women Writers</AUTHORITY>
                <AUTHORITY>Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory</AUTHORITY>
            </PUBLICATIONSTMT>
            <SOURCEDESC>Born Digital object.</SOURCEDESC>
        </FILEDESC>
        <PROFILEDESC>
            <LANGUSAGE>
                <LANG IDENT="eng">English</LANG>
            </LANGUSAGE>
            <TEXTCLASS>
                <KEYWORDS>
                    <TERM>Born digital</TERM>
                    <TERM>Life writing</TERM>
                    <TERM>Biography</TERM>
                    <TERM>Bibliography</TERM>
                </KEYWORDS>
            </TEXTCLASS>
        </PROFILEDESC>
        <REVISIONDESC>
            <WORKFLOW RESP="MRB" WORKCATEGORY="created" WORKSTATUS="C">
                <DATE/>
                <ITEM/>
            </WORKFLOW>
        </REVISIONDESC>
    </CWRCHEADER>
    <ENTRY>
        <HEADING SUBTYPE="1">NERVE CWRC Entry Test File - short, with pre-existing entity tags (1861-1922)</HEADING>
        <RESEARCHNOTE><XREF URL="http://www2.ville.montreal.qc.ca/archives/portraits/en/cards/P0621.shtm" RESP="KME">Sara Jeannette Duncan in 1909</XREF>. Image from The Lounger, Putnam's and the Reader 5 (October 1908-March 1909): 502-3.</RESEARCHNOTE>
        <AUTHORSUMMARY>
            <P>Ontario-born Sara Jeanette Duncan achieved considerable recognition for her many ironic novels and other writings that draw on her experiences in Canada, the US, England, and India.</P>
        </AUTHORSUMMARY>
        <BIRTH>
            <CHRONSTRUCT> <DATE VALUE="1861-12-22">22 December 1861, </DATE> <CHRONPROSE>Brantford, ON </CHRONPROSE> </CHRONSTRUCT>
        </BIRTH>
        <DEATH>
            <CHRONSTRUCT> <DATE VALUE="1922-06-22">22 June 1922, </DATE> <CHRONPROSE>Ashtead, Surrey, England </CHRONPROSE> </CHRONSTRUCT>
        </DEATH>
        <PERSONNAME>
            <HEADING SUBTYPE="5">Name at birth: </HEADING>
            <DATASTRUCT>
                <DATAITEM><BIRTHNAME> <GIVEN>Sarah Janet</GIVEN> <SURNAME>Duncan</SURNAME> </BIRTHNAME> </DATAITEM>
            </DATASTRUCT>
        </PERSONNAME>
        <PERSONNAME>
            <HEADING SUBTYPE="5">Variant names: </HEADING>
            <DATASTRUCT>
                <DATAITEM>Mrs. Everard Cotes</DATAITEM>
                <DATAITEM>Jeannette Duncan</DATAITEM>
                <DATAITEM>S.D.</DATAITEM>
                <DATAITEM>"Civilis"</DATAITEM>
                <DATAITEM>"Garth Grafton"</DATAITEM>
                <DATAITEM>"Jane Wintergreen"</DATAITEM>
                <DATAITEM>"V. Cecil Cotes" </DATAITEM>
            </DATASTRUCT>
        </PERSONNAME>
        <FRONT>
            <P></P>
            <P>Entry revised by Karyn Huenemann and Linnea McNally</P>
            <HEADING SUBTYPE="2">Sara Jeannette Duncan (1861-1922)</HEADING>
            <P>Sarah Janet Duncan was born on 22 December 1861, the eldest of nine surviving children of Charles Duncan (1834-1907) and Jane ("Jeannie") Bell (1837-1931). She enjoyed a prosperous upbringing due to her father's success as a merchant. She first attended Central School and Brantford Ladies College, and then trained as a teacher at the Brant County Model school, earning her third-class teaching certificate in 1879. She taught school in the Brantford area from 1880 to 1882.</P>
            <P>Her first published prose piece, "Diogenes on Bric-a-Brac," appeared in The Canadian Monthly and National Review in June 1880.<BIBCITS> <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:8b2de07f-7b41-4cf3-b458-292a4a06f0bc"></BIBCIT> </BIBCITS> With an early desire to distinguish herself in literature, she chose to pursue a journalistic career, establishing herself with articles about the New Orleans Cotton Centennial of 1884 in the London Advertiser (Ontario), the Toronto Globe, and the Memphis Appeal. She left New Orleans in May 1885 in order to work in a variety of journalistic roles, including some occasional writing for the Globe and full-time work on the Washington Post from October 1885 until the spring of 1886. She became one of Canada's first regular woman journalists with a daily column in the Globe, entitled "Woman's World," and later wrote a similar column, "Bric-a-Brac," for the Montreal Star. Working at the Star from the fall of 1887, she was made the Star's parliamentary correspondent in Ottawa in March 1888. She continued to contribute to periodicals such as The Week, where she used the pen name "Garth Grafton."</P>
            <P>Having altered her name to what she considered the more sophisticated "Sara Jeannette," she published her first novel, A Social Departure, in 1890. The novel originated as a series of travel sketches written for the Montreal Star in 1888-89, as she travelled around the world with fellow journalist, Lily Lewis. In India, Sara met Everard Cotes, a Calcutta museum official who later became a newspaper editor and Reuters correspondent. Sara completed her journey, staying with Everard's relatives in England before returning to Brantford. In the autumn of 1890, Sara travelled back to Calcutta, where she married Everard, in St. Thomas's (Free School) Church, on 6 December 1890.</P>
            <P>Duncan subsequently published serious and comic fiction set mainly in England and India, much of it concerned with Anglo-Indian social and political situations. Many of her novels, especially her earlier works, were first serialized in British and American journals (notably The Lady's Pictorial and the American edition of the Illustrated London News). </P>
            <P>In keeping with the custom of the British in India, the Cotes shared their time between Calcutta and Simla, a small Himalayan town that became the headquarters of British administration each year during the hot season. During her time in India, Sara frequently visited England for extended periods, spending almost as much time in London as in India. She also travelled home to Canada a number of times. Living in Canada, India, and England gave her a unique perspective on issues of empire, both social and political. In the late 1890s, Sara contracted tuberculosis and spent months in her Simla garden, exiled from the house, writing a reflective novel on the experience: The Crow's Nest (1901; published in England as On the Other Side of the Latch).</P>
            <P>Only two of her twenty-two novels deal with Canada: The Imperialist (1904) presents a serious analysis of Canadian identity, while Cousin Cinderella (1908; originally intended to be titled A Canadian Girl in London) takes a lighter look at international social relations. In her later years, Sara wrote plays, many of which were performed, but all of which remain unpublished. She retired with her husband to Chelsea, in London, then to Ashtead, Surrey, where she died of pneumonia on 22 July 1922. She was buried in St. Giles churchyard, in Ashtead, on 26 July 1922.</P>
            <P>For a more detailed biography, see her entry in the Dictionary of Canadian Biography.</P>
        </FRONT>
        <HEADING SUBTYPE="2">Published Texts</HEADING>
        <HEADING SUBTYPE="3">Fiction</HEADING>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:56b2b8ea-a322-473b-ab85-17c98aeb5d05"><XREF URL="https://archive.org/details/cihm_05297" RESP="DJW">The Story of Sonny Sahib</XREF> (London: Macmillan, 1894; New York: Appleton, 1894)—as Mrs. Everard Cotes (Sara Jeannette Duncan); first serialized in Youth's Companion (Boston, MA)</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:2c37db05-78e1-4810-a593-9459c7c49b9c"><XREF URL="https://archive.org/details/vernonsauntbeing00duncuoft" RESP="DJW">Vernon's Aunt</XREF> (London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1894; New York: Appleton, 1895)—as Sara Jeannette Duncan (Mrs. Everard Cotes); first serialized in The Idler</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:95744622-be63-40ca-8638-cb52ee614799"><XREF URL="https://archive.org/details/thosedelightfula00duncuoft" RESP="DJW">Those Delightful Americans</XREF> (New York: Appleton, 1902; London: Methuen, 1902)—as Mrs. Everard Cotes (Sara Jeannette Duncan); first serialized in Ladies Field (London)</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:93bcabdf-c076-4907-ab9b-2612a371d169"><XREF URL="https://archive.org/details/poolindesert00duncuoft" RESP="DJW">The Pool in the Desert</XREF> (New York: Appleton, 1903; London: Methuen, 1903)—as Mrs. Everard Cotes (Sara Jeannette Duncan); the title story first published in Century Illustrated (New York)</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <HEADING SUBTYPE="3">Plays</HEADING>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:261ffa42-4104-487b-8012-b3fdca6da896">Beauchamp and Beecham: A Comedy in Khaki. In Three Acts&#8212;performed at the Lyric Theatre, London, 1915</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:e1235356-a490-4575-90fd-1126237495d9">Billjim from Down Under—performed at the Tivoli Theatre, Adelaide, Australia</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <HEADING SUBTYPE="2">Periodical contributions</HEADING>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="">Athen&#230;um (London)</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="">Atlanta</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="">Canada Monthly</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <HEADING SUBTYPE="2">Residences</HEADING>
        <RESIDENCEANDMOBILITY RELATIONTO="LIVED">
            <P>Ashtead, Surrey, England (1920-1922) </P>
            <P>Brantford, ON, Canada (1861-1884, 1886) </P>
        </RESIDENCEANDMOBILITY>
        <HEADING SUBTYPE="2">Education</HEADING>
        <EDUCATION MODE="INSTITUTIONAL">
            <P>Central School, Brantford, Ontario</P>
        </EDUCATION>
        <HEADING SUBTYPE="2">Archival Holdings</HEADING>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:2abdc111-a890-41e6-b79e-b41d6013ef80">A.P. Watt &amp; Company Records, Library of University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, USA</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:914a68e1-9978-477b-9586-3fda2f459649"><XREF URL="http://findingaids.library.dal.ca/archibald-macmechan-fonds" RESP="KME">Archibald MacMechan fonds</XREF>, Dalhousie University Archives, Halifax, NS (letter to Archibald MacMechan)</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <HEADING SUBTYPE="2">Published Resources</HEADING>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:721ab6f9-d214-4e19-aa72-398ee0136874">1841 England Census.</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
        <LISTBIBCIT>
            <BIBCIT REF="http://commons.cwrc.ca/islandora:59f1331c-9b89-4ff9-b6e6-14accd03877b">1861 England Census.</BIBCIT>
        </LISTBIBCIT>
    </ENTRY>
</CWRC>
